A Guide to the Papers of Carter Glass 1858-1946, and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Miscellaneous correspondence 1919-1925 (Box 142)
  D. Miscellaneous correspondence, 1919: Patronage; Discharges; Numerous complaints from grocers against the large packers; Material on the federal regulation of packing industry.
- Correspondence and announcements regarding the Civil Service Commission and the Peace Treaty 1919-1921 (Box 143)
  A. Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1919-1920: Some civil service material; The remainder nearly all concerned with ratification of Treaty of Versailles.
  B. Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1920-1921: Additional civil service material and requests from constituents for job assistance; Treaty of Versailles material, including printed speech by Senator Henry Cabot Lodge and printed copy of various reservations introduced by Lodge.
  C. League of Nations and Peace Treaty: Telegram from Frederick A. Delano, congratulating Carter Glass on his article on the peace treaty which had appeared in the New York Times; Booklet, "The Meaning of War and the Basis for Permanent Peace," by James W. Johnson; copy of a letter from Carter Glass to Theodore Warburg on March 17, 1920, in which he indicates a knowledge of the attitude of President Wilson on certain amendments to the peace treaty;"Comparison of the Plan for the League of Nations, " 1919, 4 copies; "Treaty of Peace with Germany, " 1919, 2 copies; "Hearing Before the Committee on Foreign Relations, United States Senate, Part 17," 1919, one copy.
- Correspondence concerning legislative and Treasury matters 1919-1922 (Box 144)
  A. Correspondence with Joseph P. Tumulty, secretary to the President: Note, January 14, 1920, stating that the President had not yet decided upon a successor for Carter Glass as Treasury Secretary and requesting that Carter Glass remain at the job for awhile longer; Tumulty sent an editorial taken from the Newark Evening News, January 27, 1920, in which the criticisms of Charles N. Fowler, concerning the Federal Reserve System, are discussed; Tumulty sent a copy of a letter from Senator Robert L. Owen to President Wilson on November 6, 1919, concerning the desirability of correcting an adverse balance of trade; Newspaper article in which Representative Edmund Platt proposed removing from the Federal Reserve Act those elements which William Jennings Bryan had suggested; Other correspondence from J. P. Tumulty at the White House.
  B. Several notes from Robert Lansing, Secretary of State.
  C. Correspondence with Daniel C. Roper, Commissioner of Internal Revenue: Letter from Roper to William G. McAdoo on August 12, 1919, reporting on events since McAdoo had left the Treasury Department; Copy of a confidential report from Daniel C. Roper on February 1, 1919, concerning the method of meeting government obligations, incurred in anticipation of revenue from quarterly payments of income and excess profits taxes, which had since been canceled.
  D. Correspondence with William G. Redfield, Secretary of Commerce: Correspondence concerning the proper performance of Treasury functions in connection with foreign exchange; Correspondence relating to the terminations of price controls.
  E. Correspondence with Charles S. Hamlin, member of the Federal Reserve Board: Correspondence regarding the question of the power of the Federal Reserve Board to change discount rates; Letter from Governor Harding, December 29, 1919, stating that acceptances are not being used extensively for rediscount purposes; Note from Charles S. Hamlin on December 20, 1919, pointing out an error in the proposed bill abolishing the sub-treasuries; Correspondence relating to the possible abolition of the Capital Issues Committee. Although he was chairman of the Committee, Charles S. Hamlin favored its abolition; Report from Benjamin Strong, governor of the New York Federal Reserve Bank, concerning replacement of United States notes (greenbacks) by Federal Reserve notes and the abolition of the sub-treasury system, sent by Charles S. Hamlin to Carter Glass for an expression of opinion from the Treasury Department. Carter Glass does not think highly of the proposal to retire greenbacks; Correspondence concerning a proposed Federal Stock Publicity bill to regulate stock promotions; Correspondence with John Skelton Williams, Comptroller of the Currency, concerning the wisdom of granting permission for the National City Bank to establish foreign branches; Note from Charles S. Hamlin stating that any refunding of debts by foreign countries should be handled by Federal Reserve banks, rather than by private bankers; Copy of a draft, prepared on February 7, 1919, of an act to "provide for furnishing information with respect to shares of stock offered to the public;" Statement of Carter Glass that he is happy to know that Charles S. Hamlin is satisfied with the appointment of Shouse as Assistant Secretary of the Treasury.
  F. Correspondence with W. P. G. Harding, Governor of the Federal Reserve Board: Copy of an address to be delivered by Harding to a Pan-American Financial Conference; Statement by Harding in which he refutes a claim by J. A. Pondrom that small banks are being discriminated against by the requirement that checks be cleared at par; Letter from W. P. G. Harding on November 12, 1919, suggesting that Carter Glass introduce legislation designed to stop the circulation of checks bearing a statement that the check would be paid at the current exchange rate; Memorandum from Harding to Carter Glass, citing a problem in which the cities of Lynchburg and Roanoke, Virginia, were involved, concerning immediate payment of checks at Federal Reserve banks, if excess reserves sufficient to cover this service were maintained; A report to the President by Senator Robert L. Owen on February 27, 1919, suggesting that the dollar be put at par with the money of other countries by the issue of government securities payable in foreign currency, is referred to Carter Glass through a personal note from Woodrow Wilson. The opinion of W. P. G. Harding on the question is presented in a letter to Carter Glass, then Secretary of the Treasury; A copy of a statement, encouraging use of credit by the construction industry, which Warren G. Harding sent to Leffingwell with the suggestion that a similar report be issued by the Treasury Department; Notes by which Carter Glass agrees that Harding is too busy to continue the work involved in his connection with the War Finance Corporation and promises to have him relieved of these duties; Report prepared by Leffingwell, Assistant Secretary of the Treasury, for Carter Glass on January 3, 1919, recommending that the Federal Reserve Act be amended so that more revenue can be derived from the earnings of the Federal Reserve banks. A corresponding memorandum to Harding from M. C. Elliott, general counsel, refutes a portion of the Leffingwell memorandum; Several other notes from Harding.
  G. Correspondence with Franklin K. Lane, Secretary of the Interior.
  H. Correspondence concerning appointments to the Federal Reserve Board: List of persons and groups recommending several men for appointment to the Federal Reserve Board. Paul M. Warburg has the best recommendations; Article in the Daily Bulletin issued by the weekly newspaper Manufacturers Record, entitled, "Why Paul M. Warburg Should Not Be Reappointed on the Federal Reserve Board "; Telegram from Pierre Jay, presenting the names of many men who might possibly be appointed to the Federal Reserve Board, but questioning the availability of most of the better men on the list; Explanation of the provisions of the Federal Reserve Act with respect to qualifications for membership on the Federal Reserve Board, sent to Carter Glass by W. P. G. Harding; Correspondence running over a period of time between the Treasury Department and Evans Woollen, concerning the opportunity to fill a vacancy on the Federal Reserve Board. Woollen failed to arrive at the decision to accept the appointment, if tendered, in time to have his name presented; Refusal of W. A. Julian to accept recommendation as a member of the Federal Reserve Board; Telegram from William G. McAdoo to Carter Glass, then Secretary of the Treasury, approving the suggestion of Charles G. Dawes for nomination to a position on the Federal Reserve Board. Dawes declined; Wallace D. Simmons, St. Louis, Missouri, hardware executive, declines to have his name suggested by Carter Glass for a position on the Federal Reserve Board; John V. Farwell recommended Frederick A. Delano for reappointment to the Federal Reserve Board, but Carter Glass felt that circumstance prevented his making this recommendation to the President; Telegram from E. D. Hulbert also recommending Frederick A. Delano; F. H. Rawson refused a nomination for a place on the board; Letter of December 2, 1918, from Pierre Jay to Russell C. Leffingwell, passing on a recommendation of F. P. Hixon, with whose nomination it was said Benjamin Strong would concur. William G. McAdoo responds to an inquiry from Carter Glass by stating that he does not know Hixon; Note from Vice-President Thomas R. Marshall on January 18, 1919, stating that, if Evans Woollen or E. H. Wolcott are not available, he would suggest Leroy A. Goddard, whose appointment would be satisfactory with James B. Forgan and Reynolds. Carter Glass, however, was not inclined to propose the name of Goddard, because he was not widely known among western bankers; Exchange of telegrams with William G. McAdoo, agreeing to postpone action on appointments to the Federal Reserve Board; Albert Strauss at the Federal Reserve Board recommended J. H. Puelicher for nomination to the Board.
  I. Response to requests for copies of the Annual Report of the Secretary of the Treasury, including requests from several Senators. The Secretary of War, William G. McAdoo, Frederick A. Delano, Louis D. Brandeis, Robert W. Woolley, and John Wanamaker are among those who write to thank Carter Glass for sending them copies of the report.
  J. Correspondence involving Russell C. Leffingwell and reports prepared by Leffingwell as Assistant Secretary of the Treasury: Letter of high commendation written by Carter Glass on February 2, 1920, to Russell C. Leffingwell for his service during the term of Carter Glass as Secretary of the Treasury, paying compliments to Leffingwell in correspondence received by Carter Glass; Memoranda relating to foreign loans; Statement and newspaper articles regarding the ship building industry; Memoranda regarding the cost of living; Summary of newspaper reports about the effect of a program, introduced by Carter Glass, whereby Treasury notes would continue un use to finance government operations; Note from Russell C. Leffingwell discouraging any policy permitting public officials to get information about national bank loans from bank examiners; Memoranda concerning price levels and determination of wheat prices by the government; Copies of several summaries pertaining to Treasury activities and expected Treasury policies; Statement by Leffingwell that banks should not buy tax certificates, in anticipation of the time when income and profits taxes fall due, but rediscount the certificates before the taxes must be paid; Memoranda relating to liberty loans; Copy of a bill "to provide a national budget system and an independent audit of Government accounts," accompanied by a Leffingwell memorandum on the bill, which expresses some disfavor; Memoranda regarding the desirability of retaining certain men on jobs indirectly involving the Treasury Department and of bringing several good new men into the department; Memorandum, addressed to Russell C. Leffingwell by Fred J. Kent, Director of the Division of Foreign exchange of the Federal Reserve Board, favoring the raising of the gold embargo; Memorandum in which Leffingwell opposes tax exemptions for bonds issued by the Federal Home Loan Bank and gives his personal reasons for taking this position; Memorandum from Leffingwell to Carter Glass on May 14, 1919, opposing a plan offered by Governor Harding, whereby the Federal Reserve Board would set up an organization of its own to handle foreign exchange matters, suggesting that these things not be taken out of the hands of New York financiers, stating that the board would not be able to conduct such business satisfactorily and that this plan is similar to an earlier plan, presented by Senator Robert L. Owen, with which Harding did not agree; Memorandum opposing the establishment of an International Gold Clearance Fund and showing the effect on the Federal Reserve System; Newspaper article reporting the likelihood of a new Treasury issue similar to previous victory loans, but with no sales campaign involved. Statement by Carter Glass, concerning the method and terms of issue is included; Russell C. Leffingwell states that he hopes acceptance of the Railroad Administration will not be allowed into Reserve bank portfolios; Leffingwell expressing alarm over a statement by Governor Miller of the Federal Reserve Bank at Kansas City, criticizing governmental expenditures and fearing that the success of the Victory Liberty Loan might be jeopardized; Memoranda and printed statements concerning liberty loans; Copy of an act of January 13, 1919, in the Senate, providing for relief in cases where formal contracts had not been made according to law; Copy of an article of January 18, 1919, entitled, "Financial Experts to Advise Wilson." The problems were those occasioned by the armistice with Germany; Memorandum from the Federal Reserve Board on January 18, 1919, concerning wheat prices.
- Miscellaneous Personal Correspondence 1919-1925 (Box 145)
  A. Correspondence with Rixey Smith, secretary to Carter Glass: Handwritten letter from Carter Glass to Rixey Smith, asking him to locate certain statistics concerning loans by the Richmond Federal Reserve Bank to South Carolina banks, among certain papers retained for confronting Tom Heflin; Copy of a magazine article, listing Carter Glass as a possible Democratic candidate for the presidency in 1924 and devoting a lengthy paragraph to the reasons for considering him as an acceptable candidate; Rixey Smith wrote Carter Glass on July 6, 1923, to say that the things in his office had been properly stored away and that particular care had been taken of a package of papers concerning the Federal Reserve, about which Carter Glass had spoken; Letter from Rixey Smith, October 5, 1922, stating that President Harding would make no appointments to the Federal Reserve Board while Congress was not in session, but that he seemed to favor W. P. G. Harding, if Congressional approval were insured. Newspaper report of a speech by Reginald McKenna, former chancellor of the British Exchequer, concerning the methods by which England, France, Italy, and Germany could pay their debts, is enclosed by Smith.
  B. Correspondence with Henry C. Stuart, former governor of Virginia: Letter of July 9, 1923, from Carter Glass, stating that the circumstances under which he feels that he might be nominated for the presidency; Carter Glass to Henry C. Stuart, July 22, 1924, describing how narrowly he had missed the Presidential nomination; Exchange of letters between Carter Glass and Henry C. Stuart, September-October, 1924, regarding attempt by former Governor Westmoreland Davis to create a division between them, as a means of breaking back into politics.
  C. Letter to the editor of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, correcting an impression that, in a speech to the Richmond Chapter of the American Institute of Banking, Carter Glass had severely criticized the War Finance Corporation.
  D. Correspondence with William V. Wilson, Lynchburg, Virginia, lawyer: Letter from Carter Glass to William V. Wilson on March 12, 1920, stating that he discussed the question of increasing government deposits at the Lynchburg National Bank with Assistant Secretary Leffingwell, but received little satisfaction.
  E. Two copies of a speech of February 13, 1924, by Senator Samuel M. Ralston, on the Mellon tax plan.
  F. Congratulatory note from Carter Glass to Samuel M. Ralston on November 13, 1922, concerning his election to the Senate.
  G. Correspondence involving Jouett Shouse, Assistant Secretary of the Treasury: Copy of a letter to Jouett Shouse on June 4, 1920, from the Oklahoma branch of the Robert L. Owen for President organization, in which the claim to authorship of the Federal Reserve Act is repeated in behalf of Senator Robert L. Owen; Patronage and personal letters.
  H. Correspondence with Josephus Daniels, most of which took place while he was Secretary of the Navy: Copy of a speech by Josephus Daniels on January 8, 1920, before a Jackson Day banquet audience; Correspondence relating to the book, "Our Navy at War," by Daniels, a copy of which was sent to Carter Glass on June 27, 1922; Miscellaneous correspondence with Daniels, especially requests for military discharges.
  I. Correspondence between Carter Glass and Walter Lipmann, requesting information or making complimentary remarks.
  J. Correspondence with Christopher B. Garnett, a Washington, D. C. lawyer: Letter from Carter Glass on November 16, 1925, discrediting the members of the Supreme Court, who participated in certain decisions involving interstate commerce; Letter of introduction for Garnett to Edmund Platt, former Congressman then serving as Deputy Governor of the Federal Reserve Board; Correspondence relating to the Norfolk and Mobjack Bay Steamboat Co., run by Garnett.
  K. Correspondence with James P. Woods, a Roanoke, Virginia, lawyer, most of which concerns the possibility of a nomination for Carter Glass to candidacy for the presidency; Some local patronage and politics.
  L. Correspondence of Carter Glass in which he recommends that John W. Davis be appointed to fill a vacancy on the Supreme Court.
  M. Correspondence, February, 1924, at the time of the death of Woodrow Wilson: Copy of an editorial of February 2, 1924, when Wilson was near death, entitled, " Woodrow Wilson in History"; Carbon copies of a letter from President Wilson to Carter Glass, May 28, 1920, thanking him for sending a copy of the platform adopted by Virginia Democrats; Excerpts from a book by Woodrow Wilson, A History of the American People; Carbon copy of a note from President Woodrow Wilson to Russell C. Leffingwell, Assistant Secretary of the Treasury, on February 4, 1920, thanking him for deciding to continue his association with the Treasury Department under Secretary Houston.
  N. Correspondence with E. Lee Trinkle, Governor of Virginia: Some correspondence bearing on Virginia politics and election of Governor Trinkle, patronage, etc.
- Invitations 1919-1920 (Box 146)
  A. Invitations to attend various public functions, including several meeting of bankers organizations.
- Correspondence 1930-1937 (Box 147)
  A. Harry F. Byrd: Numerous letters, including local politics, tariffs, appointments, depression relief measures, the apple industry, prohibition; Letters and papers document the beginning of a split between Harry F. Byrd and Carter Glass and the liberal Democrats of the Franklin D. Roosevelt camp; Correspondence discussing Virginia's road situation, state political affairs, drought relief and appointment of people to various jobs in the state are treated; Correspondence involving H. G. Shirley, Highway Commissioner in Virginia, and Colgate W. Darden.
  B. Harold L. Ickes, Secretary of the Interior: Miscellaneous correspondence, including controversy over bridge at Yorketown.
  C. General Hugh S. Johnson: Mainly concerned with price fixing activities of the National Recovery Administration; Letter from the Southern Wholesale Lumbermen's Association, March 13, 1934, protesting against minimum prices for lumber.
  D. Russell C. Leffingwell of J. P. Morgan & Co.: Letters from the 1930's, commenting on the economic crisis and New Deal measures. Correspondence from Leffingwell concerning banking legislation; Thirty- page letter expressing his criticisms of proposed amendments to the Federal Reserve Act, 1932; Letter hinting at some verbal attacks on Russell C. Leffingwell by Hearst, Samuel Untermeyer and Aldrich.
  E. W. D. Mitchell, Attorney General: Correspondence regarding the Harry Goldhurst fraud case.
- Invitations and Correspondence 1920 (Box 148)
  A. Invitations extended to Carter Glass during the year 1920 to attend and address various conferences, meetings, etc.; Invitations to luncheon by public figures such as W. P. G. Harding and an invitation to speak on "Causes and Remedies of Inflation" by the Academy of Political Science; Copies of Carter Glass' answers.
- Personal Correspondence 1918-1920 (Box 149)
  A. Ca. 20 letters, 1920, congratulating Carter Glass on his appointment to succeed Martin in the Senate; Letters regarding the possibility of Carter Glass as presidential nominee at Democratic convention, 1920, mostly of a personal nature, urging him, etc.; Letter from Carter Glass to Edmund Platt, member of Federal Board, acknowledging receipt of the chair used by Carter Glass while Chairman of the subcommittee on banking in which he did a large share of his work on the Federal Reserve legislation. The chair was sent to Carter Glass' home, 1920; Letters of a personal nature; References to Virginia politics.
- Correspondence, (A) 1920-1922 (Box 150)
  A. Ca. 150 or more letters and replies, 1920-1921, requesting that Carter Glass give his attention to various special interests when the Committee on appropriations considers the amounts to be appropriated to these different interests in the budget; About 6 letters indicating a controversy over a prayer made before the Disarmament Conference by Rev. Abernathy, 1922 in which the latter failed to mention Christ, discussing strong contention over whether the failure was purposely or accidental; Letters concerning the claims of war veterans to some form of compensation; Correspondence regarding a bill "to regulate the operation of and foster the development of ratio communications in the United States, " S.4038, 1920; Copy of a decision of the Federal District Court of the Northern District of Georgia involving the Federal Reserve Bank of Atlanta. Non member banks charged the Federal Reserve Bank of trying to put the former out of business because of their no agreeing to remit at par the payment of checks; Ca. 25 letters from the American Legion asking Carter Glass' aid on various bills, especially the soldiers bonus bill, 1919-1921; Letters from people seeking employment with the government.
- Correspondence, (A) 1920-1922 (Box 151)
  A. Continuous file from Box 150. The headings include both people and topics. In folders, alphabetical order. The major things included follow: Upwards of 200 letter dated 1920-22 concerning the status and plight of the Armenian people and the invasion of their lands by the Turks; Ca. 10 letters, 1922 between Carter Glass and George W. Armstrong of Texas, who was in the process of writing a book, The Crime of '20, regarding authorship of the Federal Reserve Act, mentioning Paul M. Warburg, Samuel Untermeyer, A. Barton Hepburn, Reynolds, James B. Forgan, Festus J. Wade, John Perrin, Laughlin, Congress men Henry, etc. in the heated debate; See folder entitled, "Armstrong George. W.;" About 35 letters dating back to 1917, asking for position in Carter Glass' office; Ca. 200 letters from people and organizations expressing their views on the question of disarmament, 1920-1922; Miscellaneous requests for assistance from constituents and friends; military discharges; veterans affairs; jobs, etc.; The replies are for the most part attached to the letters. All the material in this box is segregated by use of manila folders and arranged alphabetically.
- Correspondence, (A-B) 1920-1922 (Box 152)